Guide to the John Wilson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Wilson papers
1810-1844
OSB MSS 45
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.41
(1 box)
The papers consist of correspondence concerning the publication and subscription sales of Wilson's works, especially his long poem "The Isle of Palms" (1812). In addition to letters between Wilson and the Glasgow booksellers John Smith and Son, there are also letters from subscribers, other booksellers, and customers to John Smith concerning the availability and distribution of the poem, including James and John Ballantyne and Longmans Ltd. The collection also contains a poem by Wilson, "Lines Raised to the memory of the Rev. James Grahame," and a subscription list for "The Isle of Palms."
Wilson, John, 1785-1854
Smith, John, approximately 1784-1871
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund, 1974. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOHN WILSON, 1785-1854
John Wilson was born in Paisley on May 18, 1785, and was educated at Glasgow University and Magdalen College, Oxford, from which he received his M.A. in 1810. He then took up residence at Elleray in Windermere, married Jane Penny, and devoted himself to writing poetry. The Isle of Palms, and Other Poems, was published in 1812.
In 1815 Wilson lost his inheritance due to a relative's mismanagement and returned to Scotland, where he was called to the bar in 1815. But his first interest continued to be literature, and in 1817 he joined with William Blackwood and John Gibson Lockhart to found Blackwood's Magazine. An ardent Tory, in 1820 Wilson was appointed to the Chair of Moral Philosophy at Edinburgh University through the support of his political allies. Despite the controversy that greeted his appointment, Wilson won respect as a dedicated and inspiring lecturer.
Wilson continued to be a prolific and frequent contributor to Blackwood's until the death of his wife in 1837. Some of his more popular pieces were collected and published as Lights and Shadows of Scottish Life (1822) and Noctes Ambrosianae, which appeared posthumously.
Wilson retired from his professorship in 1851 due to ill-health, and died in Edinburgh on April 3, 1854.
Scope and Contents
The John Wilson Papers contain correspondence and a few other papers mostly relating to the publication of Wilson's first book, The Isle of Palms. The papers span the dates 1810-1844 and are organized into two series.
Series I, Correspondence, is housed in folders 1-26 and arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The majority of the letters are addressed to the Glasgow booksellers John Smith & Son and concern the publication and distribution of The Isle of Palms. Correspondents include other booksellers; subscribers to the first edition; and customers of the Glasgow firm. Individual letters have been more fully described in the box and folder listing.
Folders 16-26 contain letters from Wilson himself to John Smith, Jr., who became a friend as well as a business associate. The first 28 letters date from 1810-1812 and are mostly concerned with Wilson's poetry and his keen interest in all aspects of the publication and sales of his first work. The remainder are briefer but contain personal news, requests for shipments of books and magazines, and occasional comments on Wilson's work for Blackwood's.
Series II, Other Papers, contains a holograph of Wilson's "Lines Raised to the Memory of the Rev. James Grahame;" copies of sonnets and of "The Endless Stream," all by Wilson; and a copy of the 1812 subscription list for The Isle of Palms.
Authors and publishers -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Booksellers and bookselling -- Scotland -- Glasgow; Publishers and publishing -- Scotland -- History -- 19th century; Booksellers and bookselling -- Scotland; Ballantyne, James, 1772-1833; Ballantyne, John, 1774-1821; Wilson, John, 1785-1854; Longman (Firm); Constable, Archibald, 1774-1827
- Correspondence, 1810-1844; Series I; 0.30' (0.75 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is alphabetically arranged by correspondent.
  - ANDERSON, JAMES
    - 2 ALS to John Smith, Jr.; Edinburgh, 1812 Feb (Box 1, Folder 1)
      About John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
  - ANDERSON, JOHN
    - 2 LS (in another hand), to John Smith, Jr.; Edinburgh, 1812 Feb, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      About the arrival of copies of John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
  - BALLANTYNE, JAMES, 1772-1833
    - 4 LS (in another hand) to John Smith, Jr.; Edinburgh, 1811-12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      On the printing of John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
  - BALLANTYNE, JOHN, 1774-1821
    - 5 LS (in another hand) to John Smith, Jr.; Edinburgh, 1811-12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      On John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
  - BLAIR, ALEXANDER
    - "To John Wilson", [1810?] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Holograph verse letter.
  - BLISS, ROBERT
    - ALS to John Smith, Jr.; Oxford, 1812 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Agrees to be placed on the subscription list of John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
  - CONSTABLE, ARCHIBALD, 1774-1827
    - ALS to John Smith, Jr.; Edinburgh, 1812 Feb 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - LONGMANS, GREEN, AND CO.
    - ALS to John Smith, Jr.; London, 1812 Feb 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - MANNERS AND MILLER
    - 2 ALS to John Smith, Jr.; Edinburgh, 1812 Mar, Jul (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Discusses the sale of John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
  - MUNDY AND SLATTER
    - Letter to John Smith, Jr., Oxford, 1812 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      On the publication of John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
  - PARKER, JOSEPH
    - ALS to John Smith, Jr.; Oxford, 1812 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      On his subscription to John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
  - SMITH, JOHN, JR.
    - Letter (draft) to John Ballantyne; Glasgow, 1811 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Discusses John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
    - ALS to John Wilson; Glasgow, 1811 Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      On the proofs of John Wilson's Isle of Palms.
    - 8 letters (holograph, draft) to John Wilson; Glasgow, 1810-20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Discussing Wilson's publications.
  - VINCENT, C.
    - ALS to John Smith, Jr.; Oxford, 1812 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Mr. Cooke has no objection to affixing his name to the publication of Mr. Wilson.
  - WILSON, JOHN, 1785-1854
    - 28 ALS to John Smith, Jr., Elleray, 1810-12 (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
      On the publication of The Isle of Pines and personal matters.
    - 26 ALS to John Smith, Jr.; Edinburgh, 1815-44 (Box 1, Folder 22-26)
      Letters discuss his publications and personal life.
- Other Papers, 1811-1812; Series II; 0.11' (0.25 box)
  Series II, Other Papers, is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Lines raised to the memory of the Rev. James Grahame", [1811 or later] (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Holograph.
  - "Sonnets", [1811 or later] (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    Holograph. With "The Endless Stream" and several holograph fragments.
  - Subscription list for The Isle of Palms, [1812] (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Manuscript copy. Signed by John Ballantyne, Manners and Miller, Archibald Constable, John Anderson, and William Blackwood.